A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare Interests - Youth, Series R FA327
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Youth Organizations
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Directors, 1946-1951 (Box 14, Folder 135)
    Formation of new Board; lists of candidates and data on them; invitations to join Board. Resignations; 1951 Osborne analysis of American Youth Hostels difficulties.
    See also Box 47, Folder 537.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Pamplets, 1959-1960 (Box 14, Folder 136)
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - By-Laws, 1936-1949 (Box 14, Folder 137)
    Copies of national and Massachusetts' organizations' bylaws.
    See also Box 46, Folder 515.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Incorporation, 1948-1951 (Box 14, Folder 138)
    Legal papers regarding incorporation.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Applicants for Positions and Directorships, 1947-1950 (Box 14, Folder 139)
    Mostly candidates for directorship. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Edgar B. Young.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Survey of Hudson River Valley and Horseshoe Trail, 1951 (Box 14, Folder 140)
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - E. B. Young Material, 1947-1948 (Box 14, Folder 141)
    Information and data on fund-raising; lists of contributors; letters of appeal written by John D. Rockefeller 3rd. Correspondents include E. B. Young, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    See also Box 46, Folder 516.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - E. B. Young Material, 1949-1950 (Box 14, Folder 142)
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Edgar B. Young Material, 1951-1952 (Box 14, Folder 143)
    Information and data on fund-raising; lists of contributors; letters of appeal written by John D. Rockefeller 3rd. Correspondents include Edgar B. Young, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Contributions (A-B), 1947-1954 (Box 15, Folder 144)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd appeal letters requesting contributions for American Youth Hostels. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Contributions (C-G), 1947-1951 (Box 15, Folder 145)
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Contributions (H-L), 1947-1955 (Box 15, Folder 146)
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Contributions (M-Z), 1947-1955 (Box 15, Folder 147)
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Contributions - Miscellaneous, 1948-1958 (Box 15, Folder 148)
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Appeal Letters - Internal Memos, 1947-1950 (Box 15, Folder 149)
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Contributions, 1947-1956 (Box 15, Folder 150)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd's personal contributions to American Youth Hostels.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Fund Raising, 1947-1950 (Box 16, Folder 151)
    Drafts of form letters of appeal; plan; reports; fund-raising suggestions. List of major contributors; campaign expenses; amounts collected. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Edgar B. Young, Monroe Smith, Ben Miller, Peggy Shields.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Annual Reports, 1947-1952 (Box 16, Folder 152)
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Finances, 1947-1951 (Box 16, Folder 153)
    Studies of financial problems; summary of reports of income and expenses. Correspondents include Edgar B. Young, B. W. Miller, Monroe Smith.
    See also Box 46, Folders 517-519.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Knapsack, 1940-1947 (Box 16, Folder 154)
    Quarterly publication of American Youth Hostels; scattered copies here.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Knapsack, 1947 (Box 16, Folder 155)
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Knapsack, 1947-1948 (Box 16, Folder 156)
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Knapsack, 1947-1951 (Box 16, Folder 157)
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Metropolitan New York Council, 1947-1959 (Box 16, Folder 158)
    Appointment of McDuffie as head of Board and Stanley Payne as executive director of Council. Reports; John D. Rockefeller 3rd appearance on Mary McBride's radio program. John D. Rockefeller 3rd guarantee of $10,000 Chase loan to Council.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Clippings, 1947-1954 (Box 17, Folder 159)
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Miscellaneous Publications, 1942-1951 (Box 17, Folder 160)
    Handbooks, manual, poster, miscellaneous other material.
    See also Box 47, Folder 539.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Miscellaneous Program Operations, 1950-1951 (Box 17, Folder 161)
    Memoranda, plans, organization charts, etc. Correspondents include Ben Miller, Edgar B. Young.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Press Releases, 1947-1950 (Box 17, Folder 162)
    Publicity plans; copies of releases.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Publicity, 1947-1950 (Box 17, Folder 163)
    Drafts of publicity articles; John D. Rockefeller 3rd letters of thanks to newspaper publishers. Correspondence regarding clippings, articles, American Youth Hostels publications. Pamphlet, "Public relations for American Youth Hostels Councils." Some copies of American Youth Hostel newsletter; magazine articles on American Youth Hostels; clippings. Correspondents include Edgar B. Young, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, William Goodall, Ben Miller.
    See also Box 46, Folder 520.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Publicity, 1947-1950 (Box 17, Folder 164)
    See also Box 46, Folder 521.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Monroe Smith, 1937-1951 (Box 17, Folder 165)
    Smith's feelings regarding John D. Rockefeller 3rd activity in American Youth Hostels, and Smith's change of position to "Chief Hosteler;" salary arrangement. "Freedom Train" picketing incident. Correspondence regarding American Youth Hostels developments, Youth Argosy, the Smith's trip to Europe. 1948 difficulties regarding Smith's personal expenses. Smith's resignation from American Youth Hostels, resulting financial agreements regarding Northfield House.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Monroe Smith, 1947-1948 (Box 17, Folder 166)
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Monroe Smith - Headquarters Property, 1948-1949 (Box 17, Folder 167)
    Material regarding Northfield properties.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Smith and Cornell Matters - Smith Investigation, 1949 (Box 17, Folder 168)
    Material from McLean's files regarding proposals for settlement of accounts with Smiths; disposition of Northfield properties. 1949 Auditors investigation of Smith's Real Estate and Personal Accounts.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Smith and Cornell Matters - Smith Settlement, 1949 (Box 17, Folder 169)
    Material from McLean's files.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Smith and Cornell Matters - Cornell Matter, 1947-1948 (Box 18, Folder 170)
    Legal hassle stemming from former American Youth Hostels president, Julien Cornell's purchase of building to house Metropolitan New York American Youth Hostels office.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Arthur Jones Material Regarding 1949 Survey, 1947-1951 (Box 18, Folder 171)
    Jones made study of organization's structure and administration; no copy here. Also made 1949 survey of relationship of national organization to local Councils; draft of 1949 report and recommendations. Correspondents include Arthur Jones.
    See also Box 46, Folder 522.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Travel and Transportation, 1946-1949 (Box 18, Folder 172)
    Proposals regarding transportation of hostelers to Europe; efforts to get Maritime Commission ships. Material regarding hosteling project in post-war Germany. Negotiations with various transportation companies; problem of Civil Auronautics Board regulations, need for new legislation. Relations with Youth Argosy. Correspondents include Monroe Smith, Admiral Smith, A. J. Fulbright, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, H. C. Peterson, D. Watts.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Travel and Transportation, 1949-1950 (Box 18, Folder 173)
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Boston Council, 1947-1951 (Box 18, Folder 174)
    Miscellaneous problems, needs of Boston Council. Correspondents include Edgar B. Young, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Colonel Sherwood.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Detroit Council, 1947-1951 (Box 18, Folder 175)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd visit to Detroit, his speeches there. Miscellaneous suggestions and problems of Detroit American Youth Hostels chapter. Correspondents include Edgar B. Young, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, A. B. Pfleiderer.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Detroit Council - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Talks, 1949-1950 (Box 18, Folder 176)
    Comments on John D. Rockefeller 3rd's addresses before Rotarians and American Youth Hostels; notes on talk.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - England and Wales, 1947-1951 (Box 18, Folder 177)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd sends "message" to Association to celebrate opening of York hostel. Catchpool's projected visit to the United States. Correspondence regarding sending of Americans abroad and other projects. Correspondents include E. St. John Catchpool, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Ben Miller.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - German Hostels - Schirrmann, 1947-1952 (Box 18, Folder 178)
    Letters from Germany after World War II translated by Isabel Smith and sent on to John D. Rockefeller 3rd; descriptions of conditions, attempts to rebuild hosteling. Schirrmann's appeals to John D. Rockefeller 3rd for grants for the work were declined. Correspondents include Isabel Smith, Dr. R. Schirrmann, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Pennsylvania Council, 1948-1950 (Box 19, Folder 179)
    Development of hosteling in Pennsylvania; aggravated problems of national vs. local jurisdiction. Correspondents include Howard Ambler, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Ben Miller, Donald McLean, Laurance Saunders, Edgar B. Young.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Pennsylvania Council, 1951 (Box 19, Folder 180)
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - International Youth Hostel Federation, 1949-1956 (Box 19, Folder 181)
    Sending of delegates and reports to International Conferences; declination of appeals from ex-President of International Federation, J. Catchpool. Correspondents include D. McLean, John D. Rockefeller, L. Meinlink, Bill Goodall, E. S. J. Catchpool.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - International Youth Hostel Federation - August 1950 Conference, 1949-1952 (Box 19, Folder 182)
    Correspondence including Edgar B. Young, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, and Trygvie Lie, regarding August 1950 Conference.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Potomac Area Council, 1949-1950 (Box 19, Folder 183)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd attended 1950 meeting for American Youth Hostels Council, Board of Directors, and various dignitaries interested in hosteling. John D. Rockefeller 3rd gave speech. Correspondents include William Stone, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Norman Littell, Edgar B. Young.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Potomac Area Council - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Speech, 1950 (Box 19, Folder 184)
    Text included here.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Letter to Council Presidents, 1950 (Box 19, Folder 185)
    1950 John D. Rockefeller 3rd form letter explaining American Youth Hostels difficulties, need for retrenchment and re-evaluation of goals; responses to the letter. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Edgar B. Young.
  - Youth Organizations - Youth Argosy, 1948-1952 (Box 19, Folder 186)
    Non-profit organization affiliated to International Youth Hostel Federation and run by Monroe Smith after he retired from American Youth Hostels. Arranged for low-cost transportation for groups of American hostelers to Europe. Relations between American Youth Hostels and Argosy; organization's problems. Correspondents include Monroe and Isabel Smith, Ben Miller, Edgar B. Young.
    144.82
  - Youth Organizations - Life Camps, Inc. (Trail Blazer Camps), 1941-1959 (Box 19, Folder 187)
    Organization under auspices of "Life" magazine provided free summer vacations for needy New York children - experimental camps. Regular contributions by John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1941-1952. 1952, Lloyd Sharp resigned and nature of the camps changed; name changed to Trail Blazer Camps. Correspondents include Laurance S. Rockefeller, Lloyd Sharp, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, Doris Goss, Dana S. Creel.
    144.9
  - Youth Organizations - Life Camps, Inc. (Trail Blazer Camps) - School Camp Experiment, 1948 (Box 19, Folder 188)
    Copy of "Extending Education Through Camping," - report.
  - Youth Organizations - Life Camps, Inc. (Trail Blazer Camps) - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Correspondence and Contributions, 1937-1947 (Box 19, Folder 189)
    Annual contributions made because of experimental nature of camps. John D. Rockefeller 3rd declined to join board of Outdoor Education Association (temporary name of Life Camps, Inc.); declined appeal to contribute to leadership training program.
  - Youth Organizations - Life Camps, Inc. (Trail Blazer Camps) - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Correspondence and Contributions, 1948-1957 (Box 19, Folder 190)
  - Youth Organizations - New York City Baseball Federation, 1939-1951 (Box 20, Folder 191)
    Provided playgrounds and equipment and organized baseball games to keep underprivileged boys off the streets. Correspondents include A. Jones, Charles Taylor, Dana S. Creel, Dan Chase, Arthur W. Packard, David Rockefeller, Nelson A. Rockefeller.
    144.10
  - Youth Organizations - New York City Baseball Federation, 1939-1951 (Box 20, Folder 0191A)
  - Youth Organizations - New York City Baseball Federation - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Correspondence, 1939-1945 (Box 20, Folder 192)
    Policy decision regarding giving small sums to various youth organizations. John D. Rockefeller 3rd annual $50 contributions, 1939-1946; $100, 1947-1954.
  - Youth Organizations - New York City Baseball Federation - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Correspondence, 1946-1961 (Box 20, Folder 193)
  - Youth Organizations - Yorkville Youth Council, 1948-1961 (Box 45, Folder 501)
  - Youth Organizations - Camps, 1950-1961 (Box 45, Folder 502)
  - Youth Organizations - Rehearsal Club, 45-47 West 53rd Street - Rehearsal Club, 1921-1948 (Box 45, Folder 503)
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels, 1947-1959 (Box 45, Folder 504)
  - Youth Organizations - Rehearsal Club, 1942-1958 (Box 46, Folder 511)
    "Saturday Evening Post" article about The Rehearsal Club; Saturday, September 17, 1947; 6 leaves.
  - Youth Organizations - Boys Club of New York, 1926-1958 (Box 46, Folder 512)
    Financial data for member organizations of Boys Clubs of America in New York City and notes.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels, 1948-1950 (Box 46, Folder 513)
    "The 'Guarantee' Idea." "Fortune Magazine," November 1949.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels, 1951-1961 (Box 46, Folder 514)
    American Youth Hostels - The National Award for Distinguished Service to Hosteling - Awarded to John D. Rockefeller 3rd, February 24, 1955; original award.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Bylaws, 1936-1949 (Box 46, Folder 515)
    Incorporation and name change documents for American Youth Hostel Association, Massachusetts Branch, 1934-1936; photo static copies, 4 pages.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - E. B. Young Material, 1951-1952 (Box 46, Folder 516)
    Analysis of American Youth Hostels costs on a per passholder basis.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Finances, 1947-1952 (Box 46, Folder 517)
    Income and expense trends, 1947-1951. Chart.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Finances, 1947-1952 (Box 46, Folder 518)
    Cash deeds for balance of fiscal year 1951. Chart.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Finances, 1947-1952 (Box 46, Folder 519)
    Schedule A-Z; proposed revisions of 1950 budget.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Publicity, 1947-1950 (Box 46, Folder 520)
    "The world by the handlebars," by John Kord Lagemann, n.d., n.p.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Publicity, 1950-1953 (Box 46, Folder 521)
    "Scholastic Roto" - the high school world in picture and photograph, May 1953.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Arthur Jones Material re 1949 Survey, 1947-1950 (Box 46, Folder 522)
    1) Estimated income for fiscal year 1950 (prepared August 1, 1949) 2) Income and expenses for fiscal year 1949 3) Income for fiscal year 1948 4) Expenses for fiscal year 1948
  - Youth Organizations - Gramercy Boys Club, 1934-1961 (Box 47, Folder 536)
    Index # 144.54
    Flyer describing Gramercy Boys Club, 1961.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Director, 1946-1961 (Box 47, Folder 537)
    Board of Directors - Professional Background of Interest Chart.
  - Youth Organizations - American Youth Hostels - Miscellaneous Publications, 1942-1951 (Box 47, Folder 539)
    Youth Hostel Poster for National Savings Club, England.
- Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Miscellaneous
    Appeals and invitations from local chapters outside cities of Rockefeller residence were declined. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. 1921 visit and gift to Shanghai YMCA; later developments at the Shanghai Y. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    - 1920-1954 (Box 20, Folder 194)
      See also Box 47, Folder 538.
    - 1936-1947 (Box 20, Folder 195)
    - 1955-1958 (Box 20, Folder 196)
    - 1955-1958 (Box 20, Folder 0196A)
    - 1958-1961 (Box 20, Folder 197)
    - 1958-1961 (Box 20, Folder 0197A)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Colleges, 1909-1930 (Box 20, Folder 198)
    John D. Rockefeller, Sr.'s pledges; lists of institutions to which contributions were made. Arthur W. Packard report; printed reports; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, Frederick T. Gates, Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Colleges - Russian Student Fund, 1922-1956 (Box 20, Folder 199)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution to Russian Students' Christian Association in the United States.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Aid for Chinese Students, 1925-1931 (Box 20, Folder 200)
    Needs of Chinese students; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution made through Committee on Friendly Relations Among Foreign Students. Correspondents include Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard, Charles D. Hurrey.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Aid for Chinese Students - 1930 Correspondence, 1930-1934 (Box 20, Folder 201)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Aid for Japanese Students, 1923-1931 (Box 21, Folder 202)
    Statistics on Japanese students studying in the United States; fund began as Earthquake Relief then turned to student aid. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions through Committee on Friendly Relations Among Foreign Students; requests by students. Correspondents include Kenneth Chorley, Willard S. Richardson, Arthur W. Packard, Charles D. Hurrey.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Industrial Work in China, 1921-1934 (Box 21, Folder 203)
    Reports on industrial work; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge to National Christian Council; gift of Chinese Christian literature to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Willard S. Richardson, Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur Woods, Roger Greene, Sherwood Eddy.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Industrial Work in China - Pamphlets, 1925-1932 (Box 21, Folder 204)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Industrial Work in China - January 22, 1924 Pledge, 1924-1928 (Box 21, Folder 205)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge to fund for industrial work in China; report on how fund was used.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Industrial Work in China - Mr. Eddy's Report, 1930-1938 (Box 21, Folder 206)
    Conditions in China; industrial work of Young Men's Christian Association; relation to Rockefeller Fund.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Industrial Work in China - February 10, 1931 Pledges, 1931-1937 (Box 21, Folder 207)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions to work of National Committee of Young Men's Christian Association and National Christian Council.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Letters to Servicemen, 1917-1920 (Box 21, Folder 208)
    Personal sentiments, news of Church and Bible Class; thanks for hospitality during visit to Camp Merritt. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, Pvt. James Manning, George Perry.
    See related material in Religious Interests series.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Sex Lectures - Dr. Exner, 1911 (Box 21, Folder 209)
    Distribution of "The House of Bondage," and "Panders and Their White Slaves"; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge to pay salaries of lecturers on sex hygiene to college students; reports on visits to colleges. Correspondents include J. D. Green, Charles D. Hurrey, Dr. M. J. Exner, Charles O. Heydt.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Sex Lectures - Dr. Exner, 1912-1913 (Box 21, Folder 210)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Sex Lectures - Dr. Exner, 1913-1914 (Box 21, Folder 211)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - War Work - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Visits to Camps, 1917-1922 (Box 21, Folder 212)
    Accounts of visits to Camp Dix, Camp Upton, Camp Custer, Camp Dodge, Governor's Island, and others. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. article about Camp Dix in "Army and Navy Register"; his speech at Camp Alfred Vail; declination of invitations to speak at other camps. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Robert W. Gumbel, Raymond B. Fosdick.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - War Work - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Visits to Camps - May 1918 Trip to Norfolk (Box 21, Folder 213)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. trip to Norfolk Young Men's Christian Association; memo on camps visited on inspection tour.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - War Work - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Visits to Camps - List of Camps, 1918 (Box 21, Folder 214)
    John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s visit to Camp Alfred Vail; list of camps visited.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - War Work Council - Foundation Gifts, 1917 (Box 21, Folder 215)
    Appointment of Council; application for funds for work in military and prison camps; Rockefeller Foundation contribution.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - War Work Council - Criticisms, 1919 (Box 21, Folder 216)
    Criticisms of operation of Young Men's Christian Association canteen in France; printed material.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - War Work Council - Religious Work Bureau, 1918-1919 (Box 22, Folder 217)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. membership on Bureau; agenda of activities; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. resignation.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - War Work Council - Contributions to War Funds, 1917-1918 (Box 22, Folder 218)